Nicole Herscovici

E-mail: nicoleherscovici@gmail.com

Profile

Master's student at University of São Paulo. Interested in political economy, studies related to the interface between capitalism and democracy, including research on left-wing governments and their relation to the economic elites and the rise of the far-right

Education

Master's in Political Science, University of São Paulo (USP), 2021-2023

Master's Thesis: Business' political behaviour under the Workers' Party's (PT)

administration

Advisor: André Vitor Singer

Nominated for Best Master's Thesis in the program

BA in Social Science, University of São Paulo (USP), 2020. (9/10, Class rank 2 out of 103).

Publications

"Port's war: a case of business' political sucess

Agenda Política, 2023

"Interpretations of Gramsci in Fernando Henrique Cardoso's political thought",

with Daniela Mussi (UFRJ)

Revista DADOS, 2023 (Forthcoming)

"Industrial entrepreneurs in Dilma Rousseff's first term (2011-2014):

an analysis from the newspaper Valor Econômico", with Gabriel Nunes de Oliveira (USP)

Revista Brasileira de Ciência Política, 2022

"Aspects of the New Right-Wing Extremism: The Relationship Between Capitalism

and Fascism",

Revisa Dissonância, 2022

Translations (EN to PT)

- 1. "The Twilight of Formal Democracy: Contradictions of Accumulation and the Political Crisis of Neoliberalism", by Alyson J. Ayers and Alfredo Saad-Filho (2022)
- 2. "The Age of Crisis: Neoliberalism, the Collapse of Democracy, and the Pandemic", by Alfredo Saad-Filho (upcoming, 2023)
- 3. "American Interregnum: Nancy Fraser's interview to Alessandra Spano" (2021)

Conference Presentations and Awards

1. "Ports' War: A Case of Business' Political Success"

VII Fórum Brasileiro de Pós-Graduação em Ciência Política (2022)

Awarded best paper in the studies of Political, Social and Burocratic Elites

2. "The giant woke up: The 2013 mass demonstrations and business opposition

to Rouseff's government"

XII Seminário Discente da Pós-Graduação em Ciência Política da USP (2022)

Awarded best paper in Political Theory and Political Thought

3. Textile businessmen interpretations about Rouseff's impeachment:

what are the reasons and solutions to the Brazilian crisis? 46° Encontro anual da ANPOCS (2022)

4. "The political behavior of the textile-clothing business sector in the Dilma Rousseff governments (2011-2016)"

XI Seminário Discente da Pós-Graduação em Ciência Política da USP (2021)

5. "Dilma Rousseff's administration and the business sector's opposition" 27° Simpósio Internacional de Iniciação Científica e Tecnológica da USP (2019) Awarded top 10 papers in the International Round

Teaching Experience

University of São Paulo (USP), 2021

Short course: "Brazil in crisis? Capitalism and Democracy"

with Gabriel N. de Oliveira, Alessandra Freixo, Rafael Costa and Fellipe Bernardino

Teaching assistant to undergraduate course (USP): Modern and Contemporary Political Theory, 2022

Fellowships and Grants

2020-2022: CAPES-PROEX graduate fellowship (Master's in Political Science).

2019: CNPq undergraduate fellowship

Other Professional Experiences

Research assisant to Maria Hermínia Tavares de Almeida (CEBRAP), 2022-2023.

Responsible for data collection (including archival) and analysis about the Brazilian Social Democracy Party (PSDB), its pre-electoral coordination

and electoral campaigning.

Research assistant to Ritika Goel (UC Berkeley), 2022.

Responsible for collecting and coding Jair Bolsonaro's and Lula da Silva's online campaigning

during the 2022 Brazilian elections.

Translation and proofreading of academic works

Skills

RStudio Atlas.ti Office

Languages

Portuguese (native)

English (Cambridge English Advanced; 108 TOEFL - 30R, 26L, 25S, 27 W)

Spanish (reading)

Methods and tools experience

Process tracing; media analysis; discourse analysis; Semi structed interviews (elites and bureaucrats);

Creation of database in Excel and RStudio

Analysis of national surveys such as IBGE and RAIS